hundreds of kilometres from land buried
beneath the earth's surface an untapped
energy source that could help reduce
carbon emissions
natural gas but these fields were too
remote to be accessed until now
there's gonna be a city of its own a
game-changing vessel is being built
unlike any other
[Music]
it extracts
liquefies in stores natural gas into
far-flung offshore locations and in the
future gödel imitate the need for
undersea gas pipelines is 132 thousand
tons of steel will be capable of pumping
gas from 200 meters below the ocean
National Geographic reveals the world's
first floating natural gas facility
[Music]
around 180 kilometers off the shores of
Sarawak Malaysia like the cumin canna
wit gas reserves trapped in Rock beds
almost a hundred metres deep remote gas
fields like these make up nearly a third
of the world's gas reserves till today
they remain hard to reach using
conventional methods but that's about to
change
[Music]
Petronas is building a massive floating
facility that stands 10 stories high a
game-changer on how this precious
resources mind petronas has been looking
in trying to monetize small and send the
gases for a while since 2006 it's a very
bold and courageous move that is made
there are no references and no bench one
global fortune 500 company Patronus is
Malaysia's state-owned oil and gas
company they have to address a huge
challenge that the industry faces
[Music]
volatile and highly flammable gas to
make natural gas safer to work with
massive processing plants on land will
first to cool it to a negative 162
degrees Celsius where it turns to LNG
liquid natural gas
LNG takes up six hundred times less
space making it easy to store and
transport large volumes but it's never
been done at sea one of the major
challenges basically we will be
operating equipment that SB is compared
to the onshore plan and this is the mega
factory that will achieve the impossible
it's called the P of LNG satu for the
last year this has been her home
an extensive deep-sea port on go J
Island South Korea and in 14 months this
mega vessel needs to be ready to sail
this 365 meter long gas processing plant
took ten years to conceptualize and
design the first problem how to store
dangerous liquid gas at sea and keep it
cool in the tropical heat
the solution to design colossal tanks
within the giant Hall
[Music]
it will be the first in the world
but it needs to do more than just store
the gas
but this apparently project the hull
that we designed is basically to support
such a module to be operated for 20
years with good fatigue condition
[Music]
this hall has to withstand over 48,000
tons of steel that will make up the
processing plant
[Music]
once the hall is finished the
construction team needs to build the
tanks that will store the liquid natural
gas what I want me to hide
this is basically the best time to enter
the time so this time gonna be a
dangerous thing because we will store
LNG at minus 163 degrees Celsius so
nobody can entertain
the cavernous interior can hold nearly
22,000 cubic meters of liquid the volume
of almost nine Olympic sized swimming
pools it takes 20 shipments of gas to
power almost 700 thousand households
across mega city Tokyo for a whole year
putting the tanks in the hall is an
innovative solution when it comes to
saving space but there's a danger
especially when it's partially filled
the vessels movement could create an
immense unstable sloshing of the liquid
the sloshing effect is basically if you
have a cup or a pill right you fill it
with water right and you start rockin
the pill you can see there water
sloshing back and forth with enough
force the one millimeter thin membrane
separating the LNG from the hall could
break if that first layer in the tank is
damaged the liquid could escape and
embrittle any structure it touches
for lead hull engineer Fahmy Mahmood
this is a nightmare scenario that must
be avoided if LNG come culture in the
house is very big disaster first the
house can follow and the structure also
will follow
a gas leak could lead to an explosion
and if that happens at sea it could turn
into a catastrophe
how the gas will be contained on board
is crucial to prevent masses of liquid
gas from slushing the team came up with
a unique new design
two parallel rows with four tanks in
each will help minimize the risk of
destabilizing the vessel
it is the first operational hall design
of its kind in the world
[Music]
after months of construction the tanks
are finally complete now it's time to
build a processing plant on top of the
hall to do that 21 massive prefabricated
modules need to be moved onto the ship
and assembled the last one to arrive is
a 2,000 ton mega block that will purify
the gas this is our last module to be
transported from the regression area to
the key side where the final location
before we live up on to the flow test
maneuvering these mega bloks requires a
heavy-hauler with 112 axles
[Music]
even the slightest jolt during the move
could damage the carto above
need to move slowly because we need to
make sure that the ground conditions are
synchronized and automatically level to
avoid any movement to the models
[Music]
okay Raju already arrived or no major
issue during the transportation now we
are waiting for the transporter to
setting down and then after that we
already scheduled our lifting to lift
these towering blocks under the vessel a
3600 tonne floating crane is needed
but the ship needs to turn around to
receive the next batch of modules easier
said than done it's like a puzzle we
need to plan early the sequence of
Direction one module so we we can leave
our hull turning turning the hall is
going to be a huge operation for the
team the ship is yet to be balanced out
properly and turning the vessel leaves
everyone on edge
at a height of 10 storeys strong wind
could see the vessel on balance a
potential disaster that you go
don't compare junket continue to look at
Alanna tomboys I said enough Fahmy
Mahmood and the team is gearing up for
the turn and the clock is ticking fast
we have to complete the route any
activity before any because of from
10:00 a.m. the the we speed stuff pick
up up to 15 meter per second
in order to turn the platform all
neighboring vessels have to keep a
minimum distance of 100 meters
making sure that the conditions are
right is causing worry to the safety
officer this looks like parking a car
like but in reality the whole condition
is different it's a see the risk factor
is really high one mistake
everything can go wrong so you got to
get it right at first time a massive
black vessel is too close for comfort
there's no telling how long it will take
to be moved away
and time is running out yes so what does
I deal with wind speed we expect five
knots
the team has to start soon or endanger
the vessel
construction on the world's first
floating natural gas processing facility
is almost done the next step is to lift
the remainder of the 21 processing
blocks onto her hall
[Music]
one side of the vessel is fully loaded
now she has to turn around to receive
the remaining blocks
[Music]
we have a concern about the distance
between this FLNG
with another mega block
[Music]
after a few hours the vessel causing the
holdup is finally towed away and the
vessel can now turn without obstruction
with the vessels current weight of 112
thousand tonnes for tugboats gently move
her at one nautical mile per hour
[Music]
turning the vessel on the first try is a
success everybody for the great effort
now she is ready to receive the last
three components under her Hall
[Music]
project engineer Knicks Eiffel oversees
and ensures that everything runs
according to plan
okay we come to the last three heavy
lifting for this project at the moment
there it is
the module we are going to leave it over
there and then the second hability which
is the flat our will be directed here
and then the last module will come in
between the module and a flat our
in order to lift all three components
within one week the operation has to run
perfectly to time
[Music]
to load the gigantic module onto the
hall
the work crew first has to attach it to
the crane with giant shackles
it's a lot of weight to be balanced on a
floating crane and construction engineer
Austin salmon is nervous now we are
worried about the clash point there's so
many Scarfo underneath so we also afraid
that when the asset boom when you break
some of the out fittings underneath of
this module
with almost six thousand tons hanging
off the floating crane
the atmosphere is tense
wind and movement could cause the module
to swing and damage its underside
it would take months to repair and a
huge delay to the construction schedule
okay okay
I'm relaxed no problem it's really cheap
man
[Music]
now I'm already completely lifted up
it's away from the support stool
now they will detect every line then the
particular will move up from this area
the first stage went smoothly but the
danger is not over yet
it still needs to be placed on the
vessels deck
[Music]
the work crew is standing by to receive
the module
the success of this lift will determine
whether the next walk can be lifted in
on time
[Music]
but as it reaches the deck a colossal
challenge he cannot fit under the hall
and 2,000 tons of steel is suspended in
midair
send people we cannot talk
these are broken down but we are not
sure any to diversify
[Music]
the petronas team has to think fast
the longer the 2,000 ton module suspends
in midair the higher it risks
experiencing bad weather which may cause
the module to swing damaging the vessel
and injuring the crew
at the moment we are trying to rectify
by cutting the structure and receded so
once that has been cut and we will it to
be original location
which is about 200 mm apart yeah
it seems like a simple welding job but
with huge ramifications know what you
have to do the module has been hanging
for three hours and every minute
increases the danger
for you
[Music]
the world's first floating liquefied
natural gas facility PF LNG satu is well
into its final year of construction
the vessel is beginning to take on her
final shape
but there's a problem
I don't wear had quite the dirt
a massive 2,000 ton block cannot fit
onto the deck and is hanging as workers
race to cut and reweld new legs
it's a dangerous situation
and the team's work through the night
it is 8:30 a.m. and time to check at the
new Wells mean the module can fit on the
deck
[Music]
okay nine for the day ass non can heave
a sigh of relief after overcoming a
major hurdle they are one stage closer
to the final phase of construction next
they need to connect the modules with a
massive network of pipes like things in
a body they are a vital part of the
processing plant it's through these that
gas flows through the platform to the
storage tanks I know the piping work is
a big born on the project currently we
are at 97% of construction just another
3% for condition but in anywhere in the
project though the last person is very
difficult pipe spools are preassembled
length of pipe and each spool has to be
inspected tested for cracks cleaned
and then install if cracks are found the
whole spool will have to be replaced
sounds simple enough but the ship has
35,000 separate pipe spools and taking
it pretty hard to keep track of it all
[Music]
okay have you come to join me sweetie I
heard just me it's still not just in
working on the cleaning process it's
already done
so they call us to witness the
preparation the task of keeping track of
all 35,000 pipe spools falls under the
expertise of engineer Sharif of Farah
let's say one piping is not connected
then I'd assistant killer enough we have
21 modules in this project so it's not
an easy job you need to be on your foot
all the time with so many spoons to keep
track of it's a huge job and she's one
of the few women in the team I think
it's interesting because you are dealing
with a lot of kind of people and you
need to be firm with your decision I
don't give them a chance to treat me
differently
so she is testing a huge cryogenic pipe
the welds themselves are the weakest
part and if LNG escaped the warm air
could turn it quickly back to natural
gas making it potentially explosive in
the cracks under well join the secret it
has heavy wantonness 20.6 miniature so
is the best method to touch to touch the
cracks toilet
pout or the phased-array ultrasonic
testing uses probes to send a pulse into
the weld joint if there is even a
slightest crack the pipes will need re
welding so we just monitor the welding
and the cryogenic pipe passes the
inspection and fara can move on to
another over 35,000 pipe spools now they
are closer than ever to completion the
next step is a crucial series of tests
if the vessel passes them all she will
get its license to be at sea and be
commissioned
and the job of ensuring that the vessel
functions at sea is chief commissioner
kai rule and hua Yue knows the
commissioning basically like handing
over the house that when you buy out
okay the commissioning fee will be the
last team they will make sure they like
all in order
during the commissioning stage every
little detail must be looked into the
team testing the electro chlorination
module has a leak in the pipes
it's function to clean sea water and
make it safe for human use good I know
Portobello okay okay
nevermind we keep it like this so we did
all the water from the drain
okay all right
back at the control room operators are
monitoring the progress but the leak
points to a greater problem if the team
is not careful the water pressure could
damage crucial parts of the vessel keep
on monitoring now what we're gonna do is
we're gonna get a team with the proper
tools so we're gonna arrest that Lee if
the team cannot find out why it's
leaking the sail off date could be
delayed
we having leaked from the labor class
and also from the labor transmitter so
we can opposite this activity so we
stopped all the testing
[Music]
with every stop
PFL ng satu the world's first floating
natural gas facility is well into her
third year of construction
in four months she is scheduled to sail
to her new home 180 kilometers offshore
of Sarawak Malaysia
the man who will ultimately be in
command of this platform is equal on a
Shack in laymen terms I'm the captain of
the Father
once it arrives at the final destination
you will be taken control of the
platform
[Music]
but first he needs to know the ins and
outs of this is a crucial part of the
facility here natural gas gets turned
into liquid gas through a process known
as liquefaction well a liquefaction
process the whole process is essentially
like a refrigerator you have compressors
to increase the pressure of the
refrigerant then you have the
refrigerant going through oils behind
your ft read the box but to turn gas
into LNG safely ha nice ooh I've had to
design a brand new system
in nonchalance we typically use a
propane and mixed refrigerant which has
to be produced in liquid form in a crap
space like a floating energy the
equipment's are so compactly built a
single expression can cause severe
damage July 1988 oil and gas platform
Piper Alpha exploded when liquid gas
leaked from faulty pipe work it resulted
in large oil fires that eventually
triggered further explosions that
engulfed Piper alpha within two hours
the platform collapsed and 167 men lost
their lives till today it still holds
the McCobb record of the deadliest
offshore accident
today is the arrival of the compander
this crucial part will help turn gas
into liquid for this particular
liquefaction process without the
compendious we don't get the temperature
to cool down the natural gas we don't
get the LNG
[Music]
the designer of this crucial part has
arrived to help install his
one-of-a-kind machine I was the
principal machinery designer on these
compander that are used on this ship
which was a you know a very challenging
project though it took about bucks me
one year of design work wonderful
opportunity for me to actually you know
install the product that I've worked on
for a long time twenty seven and a half
really yeah let me check one more time
this piece of equipment weighs four tons
and needs to be installed perfectly in
position
[Applause]
[Music]
a little bit more oh stop stop okay 26
and a half
[Applause]
[Music]
all right looks good guys let's put four
notes on it and light them up
[Music]
with a critical part of the vessel
installed they are closer than ever to
being seaworthy but the vessel is still
not ready to sail
back at the office chief commissioner
kai rule is getting an update from the
commissioning team on how the final
tests are going commissioning so we will
compute their generation perspective
okay
the team has yet to complete checks on
all of the machinery the team has only
two months before the weather turns to
rough for her to set sail
the leis on a mega structure of this
size can cost a fortune
yeah I think is a pressure on me because
I'm the one who coordinating with the
concept we commissioned in with QC and
of course the concession if I sleep they
shadow me the commissioning also has to
postpone she needs to say long time and
it has to be a team effort
so right now
[Music]
after a series of delays
the world's first floating liquefied
natural gas facility is 30 days away
from leaving its docks in South Korea
heading to the open ocean
its mission is to tap into untouched gas
reserves off the coast of Malaysia
there is still much outstanding
construction work the team hopes to
complete as much as they can while the
vessel is docked when its offshore
conditions will be tougher project
engineer Nix Eiffel has hundreds of
decisions to make before she can set
sail
[Music]
yeah you look like a splash with the
cable tray replaced with these pipes you
don't have time to repay another 30 days
from now anything is possible you don't
have access to be material do we have
enough material they silly you are
panting down still a lot of work to do
before we sell you it is crazy on
everybody you know one vital part the
team has left to do testing the marine
loading arms within these giraffe like
extensions are pipes that will transfer
LNG gas from the platform to another
vessel
this has never been tried at sea before
and it's all in the hands of these
remote controls challenges volatile food
if you go to pump station and you want
to fill your car with the diesel or you
know petrol you know it's the same here
the only thing is you know we are
transferring LNG you know loading led to
want to a ship
so the operators of the arms need as
much practice as possible
they are connectors are no so
[Music]
with one more item off the list the
journey to build this mega floater is
about to end
after a decade's worth of dedication and
hard work
[Music]
it's time to take the world's first
floating gas platform out to sea
the vessel is preparing to set sail from
Malaysia
and the tug masters have arrived to
finalize details thread is for tomorrow
zero seven zero zero we will cool all
the way out into the basin then we will
turn around so nothing else thank you
very much let's be clear
[Music]
today captain equinox on the challenge
of a lifetime
he is about to sail the world's first
floating liquefied natural gas facility
a huge maritime achievement so now we're
gonna bring her the next stitch of her
life where she's gonna be offshore for
20 years
[Music]
all personnel use
once she on births there is no turning
back
it's a big day for us for the project
team for the operation team as well so
today is a moment of truth we're going
to start our voyage
[Music]
[Applause]
the vessel will be connected to two
tugboats
which will tow her for nearly two weeks
to her new home at cumin Kanna wit 180
kilometers offshore from Sarawak
Malaysia and once she's there
the stakes are about to get even higher
this one-of-a-kind vessel will be put to
the test
[Music]
after two weeks of sailing the world's
first floating liquefied natural gas
facility has finally reached her home
off the coast of Malaysia
[Music]
the vessel is safely anchored with the
help of wash or engineering partners now
the final stage will begin to tap
offshore gas reserves from the bottom of
the ocean it will be the first time P of
LNG satu will be put in action in the
moment when their vision would become
reality but first they need to connect
to a pipeline 74 metres below there is a
line already three-point-something
kilometres goes that seabed so we will
we will connect at that end of the
pipeline and bring the end over here it
takes for other boats to connect the
platform to the gas field
first divers will work underwater to
connect a long hose to a pipeline at the
ocean floor the dive boat which carries
the hose will move towards the platform
finally it will be hauled up to the
platform to be connected but before they
can begin there's a problem a storm has
it
causing the vessels to be thrown around
and work to be halted
with a break in the weather it's time
for the teams to get back to work
around 74 meters below the ocean divers
are preparing the first half of the
pipeline
working in cold and dark conditions for
8-hour shifts breathing in a cocktail of
helium and oxygen
offshore diving is one of the world's
most dangerous professions
so as we see we got the both divers
working here this is diver diver - and
diver one
Rogier number seven removed that's
number seven bolt removal I just gave
one offshore rush out to get em fired up
on the on the tensioner so we can lower
the Flexi you know
dick Foreman Jimmy key will lower the
next section for the divers to connect
them together and the next 30 minutes or
so we'll be ready to start lowering down
the flexible riser which
we have a pump wait the big yellow wait
right here in a pool the weight of the
riser down
[Music]
the divers are ready
Jimmy unspools the 169 meter long hose
down to the seabed it's a 24-hour
round-the-clock job for the divers and
the team
[Music]
the two hoses beneath the surface are
now connected
[Music]
and the completed pipeline is ready to
be attached to the vessel this is the
most crucial moment of the whole
procedure the end of the hose is still
on the dive boat
to transfer the host of the vessel the
boat needs to come nearer
we're going to do our connection with
our winch now to the pudding head
when we do the transfer you're gonna see
a significant load on the edge of the
Tai Chi you keep me posted if it starts
eating sharp edges profit
but with rough sea conditions the
vessels are at risk of hitting each
other
[Music]
they have succeeded the hose has been
hauled up to the vessel once we went
very well we've got the riser now that
will be the first production line
connected to the economy
[Music]
once the pipeline is tested she will
finally be able to tap the undersea gas
fields
from her design to the execution P of
LNG satu charters waters that no other
vessel has done before