[Music]
our universe the galaxies the solar
system our home planet Earth
land sea air life where did they all
come from look up into space from our
planet and what you see is a vast cosmos
teeming with billions of stars and
galaxies turn back the clock over 13
billion years and our universe was a
very different place back then it was so
small but it could fit inside the palm
of your hand from this infant universe
everything would be created stars
galaxies and the building blocks of life
itself the calcium in our bones the iron
in our blood
the atoms for the air we breathe the
water we drink
the raw materials for our cities and
machines
naked science takes a journey through
space and time to discover how the
universe was born and how it created
everything in our world
and how eventually it will die
everything we see around us is made of
matter atoms and molecules take this car
it's a 1956 ford fairlane convertible
it's constructed from many different
materials like steel rubber and glass go
deeper and these materials are made up
from combinations of elements like iron
silicon chromium and carbon each and
every atom that makes up this car were
created by our growing universe
physicist Lawrence Krauss studies how
the atoms we see on our planet have come
to be here we really are parts Stardust
and part Big Bang dusk most of the atoms
in our body are from the cores of stars
but some of them have been around since
the earliest moments of the Big Bang so
we really are truly cosmic individuals
each and every atom was created over
billions of years as our universe
evolved so when we look at this car of
course all the atoms in this car came
from stellar explosions from supernova
processes and from stellar evolution but
that were created at different times
during the evolution of the universe
to understand how the universe made all
the raw material we see here on earth we
need to take an incredible journey and
travel back through space and time to
the moment our universe was born in the
beginning there was nothing no space no
time and then there was light suddenly a
tiny speck of light appears it was
infinitely hot inside this tiny fireball
was all of space this was literally the
beginning of time the cosmic clock was
ticking time could flow and space expand
at the earliest moments the Big Bang if
you take it back to T equals zero
everything in our universe everything we
can see all the matter and all the
energy in all of the galaxies was once
contained in a region smaller than the
size of a single atom today the idea
that our universe was once tiny
originated from the brilliant work of
American astronomer Edwin Hubble back in
the 1920s most astronomers believe that
everything visible in the night sky were
stars and they were part of our galaxy
the Milky Way but Hubble wasn't
convinced he studied a swirling cloud of
light called the Andromeda nebula and
showed that it was a star city another
galaxy far outside of our own galaxy
he showed that these other galaxies were
speeding away from ours and the further
away they were the faster they seem to
be moving the universe was expanding and
if the universe was expanding then at
some point in the past it must have been
smaller much smaller
and that it must have had a beginning
the idea of the Big Bang was born
theoretical physicist David Spergel is a
big bang expert the big bang theory is
not really a fear of how the universe
began it's really a theory of how the
universe evolved no one knows exactly
what happened during the Big Bang but
scientists do know that a fraction of a
second after the universe was born this
00:05:34,650 -> 00:05:37,890
tiny super hot fire ball was already
starting to expand we don't know how the
universe began so we start our story
when the universe was a billionth of a
billionth of a billionth of a billionth
of a minute old pretty young the
universe was the size of a marble less
than a trillion trillionth of a second
after the Big Bang the marble sized
universe was very unstable and underwent
an enormous growth spurt during this
period of incredibly rapid expansion
space was self was expanding faster than
the speed of light in the same way that
this hot glass ball inflates so did the
baby universe expanding in all
directions at once and as it expanded it
cooled
a trillion trillionth of a second after
the Big Bang the universe was small
enough to fit inside the palm of your
hand a tiny fraction of a second later
it was the size of Mars another fraction
of a second and the baby universe had
grown to 80 times the size of the earth
a trillionth of a second after the Big
Bang and our newborn universe was still
expanding but it didn't contain matter
it was pure energy
Einstein's famous equation e equals MC
squared showed that mass and energy are
interchangeable it gave us the knowledge
to build weapons of mass destruction it
also revealed how the universe created
the first matter when a nuclear bomb
explodes a tiny amount of matter is
annihilated and converted into energy in
the baby universe the exact opposite
happened it converted pure energy into
particles of matter but there was a
problem the universe created both matter
and its archrival antimatter and when
these two met they obliterated each
other the infant units was a war zone a
battle to the death between matter and
antimatter
if they mutually annihilated each other
the universe would remain full of energy
no galaxies stars planets or life
fortunately for us there was an
imbalance for every 100 million anti
particles formed there were 100 million
and one particles of matter
but there was that one extra particle of
matter leftover in each volume and that
was enough to be account for everything
we see in the universe today this tiny
imbalance led to all matter we see in
the universe galaxies stars planets even
convertibles and ourselves
[Music]
astrophysicist Carlos Frank from Durham
University in England explains we are a
little bit of debris left over from the
annihilation of matter and antimatter
were the leftovers of that process if
the universe had not developed this
slight asymmetry between matter and
antimatter the universe would have been
completely boring there will be no
structure there would be no galaxies
there would be no planets quite what
this newborn universe was like has
challenged cosmologists since the Big
Bang was first put forward now in one of
the biggest laboratories on earth they
are able to recreate conditions that
almost certainly existed an instant
after the Big Bang
[Applause]
it's called the relativistic heavy ion
collider Rick for short and it's located
at the Brookhaven National Laboratory on
Long Island
it's like a time machine taking us back
to ten millionths of a second after the
Big Bang
here scientists like Todd SATA gotta
accelerates subatomic particles close to
the speed of light and then smash them
into each other
the particles race around this
two-and-a-half mile circular tunnel in
opposite directions 78,000 times a
second and then collide inside this
giant detector bigger than a three-story
house
when they smash into each other they
generate incredible heat just like the
real infant universe we believe the
early universe was extremely hot
billions of times hotter than the center
of the Sun what you're doing when he's
smashing these nuclei together is
melting matter creating matter hot
enough to give us a glimpse of what the
very early universe was like when the
particles collide they break open and
throw out a shower of even smaller
particles it's a bit like discovering
what cars are made of by watching them
smash into each other you can raise two
retires together and smash them into
each other head on when you do that
multiple times you start to see
different patterns coming out a tire
comes out here a radiator comes out
there and before long you can start to
conclude that a race car is made up of
these certain pieces what the scientists
at Brookhaven have discovered is that
within these superheated collisions a
completely new form of matter appears
and this matter contradicts the previous
theories on the nature of the early
universe because it's not a gas it's a
liquid it was super hot 100 million
times hotter than the surface of the Sun
there was so much energy inside the
young universe that the particles
vibrated so fast that it had no
stickiness there was no friction and it
flowed perfectly this liquid is perfect
it has no viscosity in some sense it
would be the perfect motor oil except
it's a trillion degrees hot inside the
collider this amazing liquid universe
exists for only a tiny fraction of a
second the Brookhaven scientists have
succeeded in recreating conditions that
existed over 13 billion years ago
despite the universe being a perfect
liquid it was in turmoil it was full of
subatomic particles smashing into each
other releasing more and more energy
there was so much energy but unless the
particles slowed down they would never
bond and create atoms the building
blocks of matter and the universe would
never create the galaxies and stars or
even us
the universe is now one millionth of a
second old and has expanded from smaller
than the size of an atom to eight times
the size of the solar system after the
incredible turmoil of the first
millionth of a second the universe was
now relatively calm
over the next three minutes the
expanding cosmos cooled sufficiently for
protons and neutrons to bind together
and form the first atomic nuclei
hydrogen and helium these were not yet
proper atoms they were missing a vital
ingredient the electron in the hot baby
universe there were plenty of electrons
around but there was still so much heat
and energy the electrons were moving too
fast to form bonds and it would stay
that way for over three hundred thousand
years 380,000 years after the Big Bang
the universe had expanded to the size of
the Milky Way it had cooled from
billions of degrees Fahrenheit to a few
thousand as it cooled the electrons
slowed down the universe was now ready
to make its first true elements one of
the scientists who discovered this
critical moment in the story of the
universe was Arno Penzias
1963 thirty-year-old Penzias and his
27-year old colleague Robert Wilson
began work on a new antenna in New
Jersey initially they were only studying
cosmic radio waves but they would
stumble on one of the greatest
discoveries of all time as they started
to test their equipment they detected an
unexpected background noise it was
additional signal and it appeared to be
coming from the sky we eliminated very
carefully the ground even the solar
system because we did this winter to
summer seasonal variation of man-made
sources of equipment all these things
were eliminated in desperation the two
scientists began to wonder whether the
strange signal might have another more
earthly origin they found there were
pigeons roosting in the antenna and it
was covered with droppings they wanted
if the pigeons were the source of the
strange signal there was only one
solution the droppings and the pigeons
would have to go we finally got around
to removing the pigeon droppings we also
have to remove the pigeons that was a
difficult problem because they turned
out to want to come back and we mailed
them off to another site but even with
the troublesome pigeons gone the
mysterious signal would not disappear
and so we left with the inyx Kate almost
inescapable conclusion that this
radiation was coming from the sky I
could not account for it the strange
signal detected by Penzias and Wilson
would turn out to be one of the most
important scientific discoveries of all
time but the explanation for their
mystery background noise starts not with
sound but with the birth of light we
usually take light for granted but in
the early universe 13 billion years ago
we would see nothing at all light was
trapped the universe was foggy
imagine a flashlight beam in a fog of
smoke the light bounces back and forth
between the smoke particles and is
trapped in the hot baby universe a dense
fog of electrons blocked the light from
escaping but as the universe continued
to expand and cruel the electrons slowed
down protons then grabbed these calmer
electrons to form complete atoms of
first hydrogen and then helium the
universe was suddenly much less crowded
with electrons the fog lifted and light
was no longer trapped it hurtled out
across the universe creating a blinding
burst of light had we been there we
would have strongly seen this opaque
universe become transparent suddenly the
fog would lift and we would see a flash
of light coming from everywhere around
us it wasn't been a spectacular moment
over time this burst of light dimmed and
cooled and became microwave radiation it
was this faint 13 billion year old
microwave signal but Penzias and Wilson
picked up on their antenna what they
heard was the quiet echo of the moment
the universe formed the first atoms it's
really the light from the origin of the
universe we've got an old FM receiver if
you tuned between channels turn the knob
and it doesn't capture and pop to a
station that's what part there's none
you hear up that's what we called noise
if you have a good radio set one half of
one percent of that is actually the
sound with a big bang and we can also
see the moment when the first elements
were created if our television is not
tuned to a station a tiny fraction of
the noise is radiation from 13 billion
years ago but this radiation is not the
only reminder of the birth of the
universe even the water we drink is a
memento and it's kind of amazing to
think that every time we take a drink of
a glass of water we're drinking in atoms
that have been around since the Big Bang
the hydrogen atoms over the next
millions of years the young universe
continued to expand cool and get dark
again
so far the universe had only made
hydrogen and helium atoms but the world
we live in is made from more than a
hundred different kinds of elements
without them the universe would remain a
very boring place made up of only gas a
place where complex matter like planets
cars and people could never develop the
universe needed to get hydrogen and
helium atoms to fuse and to do that it
needed to make stars the universe was
now 200 million years old and billions
of light-years across its temperature
had dropped so far that it was colder
than liquid nitrogen minus 367 degrees
Fahrenheit it was also dark it would
have remained a very gloomy place full
of gas but without galaxies stars or
planets if it hadn't been for one thing
the baby universe wasn't born perfect
Carlos Frank has created an amazing 3d
simulation of how the early universe
evolved it shows that when the universe
emerged from the Big Bang it was uneven
little cracks appeared which were very
very very tiny very very small and it
was his rash in the face of the baby
universe that later developed into the
patterns that we see in the galaxy's
today without these cracks the universe
would have been a very dull place the
first clues as to how these cracks
developed into galaxies and stars came
when other scientists started to examine
the Big Bang radiation first discovered
by Penzias and Wilson so it pens east
wilson saw was this radiation was as far
as they can tell uniform what
cosmologists then did for the next 25
years was work very hard to try to find
tiny variations and find them they did
using W map a space probe designed to
detect and analyze in detail variations
in the background microwave radiation
launched in 2001 the 150 million dollar
Pro fitted with some of the most
sensitive instruments ever carried into
space
our eyes detect only visible starlight
but w map can tune into the invisible
microwave radiation once in orbit around
the Sun it picked up the faint radiation
that has been rippling around the
universe since the dawn of time so when
we look at the cosmic background
radiation we're looking at this
radiation that's been streaming towards
us since half a million years after the
Big Bang initially the microwave
universe looked very dull and seemed to
be the same everywhere but when W math
turned up contrast the results were
spectacular the baby universe wasn't
smooth and boring at all it was full of
fluctuations these tiny fluctuations
tell us what the variations in density
how much stuff there isn't that how it
varies from place to place these denser
regions are going to collapse to form
clusters of galaxies and super clusters
and galaxies themselves these
low-density regions these will of grow
would become the empty regions between
galaxies so this picture really is our
connection between the universe when it
was a baby half a million years old to
the universe today 13.7 billion years
old these tiny imperfections in the
fledgling universe would become galaxies
and stars and is one of the most amazing
propositions in physics the idea that
galaxies like a milky way that contain a
hundred million stars once began life as
a tiny little crack in the fabric of the
universe the material in these cracks
was filled with swirling clouds of
hydrogen atoms
the voids between the clouds grew bigger
and bigger the gas clouds got denser and
hotter gravity pulled the gas clouds
together on filaments like beads on
threads of a web cosmic web where the
giant filaments formed large globs stars
and galaxies would grow as a universe
evolved gases were able to condense into
clouds which collapse to form stars the
star settle into a rotating disk that
was lated to become a spiral galaxy like
the Milky Way over millions of years the
hydrogen atoms clumped together and
heated up the atoms began fusing and
releasing energy and the gas cloud
started to burn brightly eventually a
star was born all over the universe
millions of stars ignited for the first
time the appearance of the first stars
would have been a cheesy spectacular
event how do we be in there we would
have really seen fireworks individual
enormous flashes of light generated as
the stars are born and burned themselves
out the universe has expanded many
trillions of times its original size
it was full of newborn stars made of
hydrogen and helium these young stars
were nothing like our own son they were
very unstable but it was their
instability that would make the universe
a more interesting place because deep
inside each new star something amazing
was happening they were creating new
elements the idea that stars build adams
came from the british astrophysicist sir
fred hoyle one of the greatest
astronomers of the 20th century Hoyle
didn't believe that the universe began
in a single explosion in fact he coined
the name big bang as a term of derision
Hoyle wanted to know where the elements
heavier than hydrogen and helium came
from he figured out that stars acted
like nuclear reactors working a bit like
a hydrogen bomb in slow motion
but many billion times more powerful and
their nuclear waste was new elements but
it would take years before scientists
were able to confirm his theory by
analyzing the light from stars each
element emits a light at a particular
frequency when heated up imagine a
sodium street lamp it emits light of a
yellow color specific to sodium it's the
same with stars take our son if you
break the light down into a spectrum you
can see lines like a bar code
corresponding to the elements each
element has specific colors helping
scientists identify elements like
hydrogen which emits mainly red light we
are go for maiden in 1990 nasa launched
the Hubble Space Telescope to unravel
some of the mysteries of our early
universe the face shuttle Discovery with
the Hubble Space Telescope
hubbell promised scientists
unprecedented views of the young
universe it would be able to look back
through space and time and examine early
stars to discover if they were making
new elements but the dream soon turned
into the worst nightmare after it was
launched they discovered that Hubble's
mirror was distorted and saw everything
out of focus it needed corrective lenses
and the only way to fix it was to send
up another space shuttle one of the
repair man was astronaut Jeff Hoffman we
were working with a two billion dollar
telescope and the last thing we wanted
was to break something and leave it
worse off than when we got up there
first the crew of the rescue mission had
to capture the crippled telescope
[Music]
then execute a repair mission
unprecedented in the history of space
flight first they had to open the access
doors on the side of the telescope the
one thing about working on Hubble that
is very different from working on a car
is you look over your shoulder and there
you are in space the earth is going by
below you the stars above you the
astronauts had to carry out fine
detailed work in the most difficult
conditions when you're working in a
spacesuit your hands are encumbered by
thick stiff gloves it's sort of like
working in ski mittens then it was quite
a challenge all went well until Hoffman
attempted to close the huge access doors
I just had to close up the doors and
when I went to close them but they
wouldn't close properly the doors were
somewhat warped and it took a while for
it to sink in this was very serious if
you can't get the doors closed you lose
the telescope using improvised tools
Jeff and a colleague were finally able
to close the doors
it took the team five days to repair the
stricken telescope cosmologists around
the world held their collective breath
they waited to see if the most expensive
telescope ever built we'll deliver when
its designers originally promised
[Music]
I well remember New Year's Eve 1993
December 31st when my phone rang and it
was an old friend who worked at the
Space Telescope Science Institute in
Baltimore he said Jeff you have any
champagne left over from your party I
said yeah we still have a half bottle in
the refrigerator said will crack it open
again and drink a glass because we got
the first picture back and Hubble works
this is what Hubble saw the images were
beyond anyone's wildest dreams
hubbell captured the final moments of a
star's life when it explodes and blows
off gas and dust it also captured inter
stellar nurseries of newborn stars
exploding into life billions of years
ago and dark pillars of cosmic dust
millions and millions of miles long
ready to spawn a new generation of stars
and planets I guess it's hard to surpass
the famous pillars of creation in the
Eagle Nebula where you actually see the
birth of stars immunity it's almost
biblical let there be light and I still
kind of get goose bumps when I look at
it but Hubble's true moment of glory was
still to come over a ten-day period in
1995 the mission controllers pointed the
telescope at a distant empty patch of
space what emerged was the Deep Field
image a tapestry of distant galaxies
Hubble was looking back in time to some
of the first galaxies and stars created
it revealed thousands of galaxies that
hadn't been seen before so the the
universe became to our consciousness far
richer after the Hubble Deep Field it
showed for the first time faint images
of galaxies form just a billion years
after the Big Bang scientists then
examined the spectrum of light from
these distant stars and showed that
these early galaxies had already created
elements heavier than hydrogen and
helium sir Fred Hoyle may have been
wrong about the birth of the universe
but he was absolutely right about the
stars the early stars acted like giant
thermo nuclear reactors creating new
elements you can think of the creation
of all the elements this room is in some
sense like a car assembly line because
in a car assembly line each part is
sequentially added to the vehicle until
it's complete
fusion reactions inside these young
stars released enormous amounts of
energy and heat which forced atoms to
fuse to form new heavier elements one
after the other three helium nuclei
combined to form carbon to carbon nuclei
fuse to form magnesium magnesium to form
neon and so on over a period of hundreds
of thousands of years until silicon
fused to form iron iron is a very
special animal the protons and neutrons
inside its nucleus are very tightly
bound together so that even the extreme
temperatures inside the stars couldn't
get it to fuse into heavier elements it
resolute listes iron it was the end of
the road the production line of element
building shut down but our universe was
still not complete there were all the
ingredients to make a glass of water and
some of the elements to build much of
our convertible there were also quite a
few of the ingredients to make a human
being the oxygen we breathe the calcium
in our bones and the iron in our blood
but there still weren't any of the vital
ingredients like chromium for our car
fender and some metals like zinc that
our bodies can't survive without the
universe was about to enter a super
creative phase where it produces all the
elements heavier than iron to make the
missing pieces in our birth of the
universe jigsaw would take some of the
most powerful explosions the universe
has ever seen
our universe has already celebrated its
500 million birthday there are still
another 13 billion more to go before
humans appear on the face of the earth
giant new stars have made many of the
elements in the world we see around us
but some vital elements are still
missing heavy metals like chromium and
zinc and expensive ones like gold and
platinum to finish the job the universe
conjures up the most amazing phenomena
since the Big Bang massive exploding
stars called supernovas when the giant
stars that made the lighter elements ran
out of fuel they collapsed in on
themselves creating incredible amounts
of energy and enormous explosions these
explosions were so powerful they could
fuse elements even heavier than iron and
restart the element production line Tony
met zacapa from Oak Ridge National
Laboratory in Tennessee believes that
without exploding stars life itself
would not exist life as we know it
certainly would not exist were it not
for core collapse supernova events they
are very clearly one of the key links in
our chain of origin from the Big Bang to
the present day one of the most recent
and biggest supernovas closest to our
galaxy was seen in the southern
hemisphere in 1987 when a supernova like
1987a explodes it emits light containing
the signatures of the elements within it
by examining this spectrum of light
scientists can calculate what elements
are being forged inside the exploding
star Michael Smith from the experimental
astrophysics group at oakridge then
recreates these events inside his own
star laboratory in this 100-foot Tower
he accelerates and smashes individual
particles into each other just like
inside a supernova a sub atomic nuclei
are the ones that are absolutely crucial
in the formation of the heaviest
elements so the idea is to measure
exactly how fast these nuclei will fuse
together in the laboratory and then
translate that information into how fast
the fuse inside exploding stones when
the particles collide inside the
accelerator they generate enormous
energy in these extreme conditions the
particles fuse and then you can bring
other particles in and they will feels
and we believe that exploding stars are
just right to form elements much heavier
than iron going all the way up to the
top of the degree audit table using the
data from these experiments Tony met
zacapa has created a model of how these
massive exploding stars turn into heavy
element factories
massive stars have evolved to an onion
like configuration at the end of a line
they have an iron core and outside of
the iron core are layers of successively
lighter elements inside the iron core
the temperature rises to eight billion
degrees nearly 300 times hotter than the
center of the Sun it is so hot the iron
atoms that have sunk to the Stars core
are torn apart the core destabilizes the
cores then collapse on themselves in a
fraction of a second the collapse
proceeds to very very high densities the
core collapses at speeds of more than
43,000 miles per second a volume the
size of the earth crunches down nearly
six times the size of Manhattan in an
instant the core becomes super dense if
one were to take one cubic centimeter of
that matter that would be the size of a
sugar cube that sugar cube would be so
dense that it would weigh as much as the
entire human race the core rebounds like
a compressed rubber ball and launches a
massive shockwave the shockwave hurdles
out smashing through the different skins
of the star
as it punches through the outer layers
of the star the energy generated
restarts the element production line
atoms are smashed together to make brand
new heavier elements all heavier than
iron then the star explodes and the
shock wave pushes the shrapnel like
debris outward further and further into
space in a very real sense our lives
depend on the stars in the universe
without their lives and deaths we would
not be here today these astonishing
images taken by the Hubble Space
Telescope show the aftermath of these
giant explosions nebulae giant clouds of
debris thrown off by exploding stars
swirling inside our big new atoms gold
silver zinc and lead without supernovas
our world would be a very dull place and
possibly lifeless
so I'm sure that that Paris Hilton
doesn't wake up every day thinking about
this fact but really if it weren't for
exploding stars those 200 million stars
that exploded so we could be here today
she wouldn't have anything to wear so if
it weren't for those supernova
explosions there wouldn't be any bling
nine billion years after the Big Bang
and all the ingredients are in place for
life as we noted the universe has grown
up into a vast complex place made up of
billions of galaxies and uncountable
stars in a quiet corner of the Milky Way
a mass of dust and gas begins to
accumulate it's full of the rich debris
left over from one of the massive
supernovas and when it reaches a
critical mass it begins to burn brightly
a star is born our own star the Sun
what's left over forms a disk of
swirling debris in orbit around the new
star the gas and dust that make up this
wrinkle I pulled together by gravity the
clumps of dust and gas become bigger and
bigger planets form one of these planets
is our earth over the next five hundred
million years our planet slowly
generates a protective canopy of gas the
atmosphere the first life appears just
single cells at first but as the eons
pass those tiny single cells evolved
into plants and animals and eventually
humans we tend to disassociate ourselves
from the universe but that of course is
completely wrong we are a vital part of
the cosmos and so when we talk about the
origin and evolution of the universe
we're actually talking about the origin
and evolution of ourselves everything we
can see on our planet was either made in
the Big Bang or inside a star scientists
like Krauss believe they now know the
genesis of every atom that has created
the world we live in these atoms have
been around since the dawn of time and
when am I was young my mother used to
tell me don't touch that you don't know
where it's been and she would have been
amazed but this is not the final chapter
in the story after almost 14 billion
years the universe has really only just
gotten started
now we take a journey into the future to
see how it all ends
the universe we live in is nearly 14
billion years old it has created the raw
materials for everything we see around
us the Stars the planets trees cities
automobiles even us our world is
complete but the universe is still
evolving scientists have come up with
many theories on how it will end we know
our universe began at a big bang what we
don't know yet is what the future of our
universe is could be our universe may
end with a bang or a whimper or
something even more exotic one theory
suggests that our universe will run out
of steam and stop expanding every star
galaxy and planet every atom will start
to collapse ending in a single super
dense pinpoint known as the Big Crunch
to find out if the universe really is
going to crash back in on itself
scientists first need to discover if
it's still expanding or if it's slowing
down astrophysicists Saul Perlmutter
studies the death of the universe by
finding beacons in space exploding stars
called type 1a supernovas if you have
enough of these exploding stars these as
the supernova that you've measured their
brightness though the ones that look
fainter and fainter and fainter must be
further and further and further away and
so you have some super know that little
brighter there're more nearby some that
are a little bit fainter so they're
little bit further and some that are
very faint so they're very far away type
1a supernovas are similar to the
supernovas that created the heavy
elements they differ in one important
fashion they always explode with the
same exact brightness this is because
they are created in the same way two
stars circle each other held together by
their gravitational attraction one is
shriveled and super dense glowing with
white heat a white dwarf the other star
has bloated to an enormous size it's a
red giant that is burning the last of
its fuel
as the two stars orbit each other the
white dwarf sucks gas from its companion
and begins to grow year after year when
it is precisely one point four four
times the mass of our Sun the white
dwarf crumples collapses then explodes
releasing a blinding burst of energy
every type 1a supernova explodes at the
same tipping point and so are equally
bright and visible across the vast
distances of the universe Perlmutter
needs to find hundreds of type 1a
supernovas and then measure how fast
they are moving away from us he links up
the most powerful telescope on earth
with the most powerful in space using
advanced cameras on the Hubble Space
Telescope and a giant telescope
officially known as The Very Large
Telescope or VLT for short he hunts for
supernovas once Hubble has detected a
particular light source colleague Chris
Lydman at the VLT analyzes the object to
see what it's made of and make sure it's
a type 1a supernova this object is is a
distant galaxy and next to it is what we
believe is a distant supernova the next
crucial step is to understand what type
of supernova this is the VLT breaks down
the light from the object into its
spectrum you want to be able to break up
its light into a spectrum and look for
the very characteristic fingerprint that
you would see on if it really were eight
a type 1a supernova
the light emitted from this particular
supernova reveals that it's a type 1a
Lydman can now calculate how far away
this supernova is the supernova exploded
about 7 billion years ago by comparing
the positions and dates of all these
supernovas stretched over space and time
Perlmutter can calculate whether the
universe is slowing down his results are
a shock the expansion of the universe
isn't slowing down at all when we began
the project of course the goal was to
find out how much the universe was
slowing down now but we actually started
looking at the data it looked like the
universe wasn't slowing enough to come
to a halt and in fact it wasn't slowing
very much at all and in fact when we
finish the analysis it looked like it
wasn't a slowing period it was actually
speeding up its expansion Perlmutter's
astounding discovery means that the
universe will not grind to a halt then
crunch back down into a pinhead of super
dense matter
quite the opposite it will continue to
expand faster and faster our universe is
literally flying apart the expansion the
universe will accelerate it ever faster
and faster rates until literally
everything will get ripped apart not
just galaxies but eventually matter the
earth all the objects stars the earth
planets people atoms in a finite time
would get ripped apart
[Music]
long after our son has burned out a
hundred billion years in the future
galaxies will pull apart the universe
will be made up of isolated stars which
are running out of energy some will
become white or brown dwarfs others will
collapse into neutron stars or black
holes then thousands of trillions of
years after the Big Bang even the black
holes will evaporate an all matter will
decay to its basic ingredients atoms
will fall apart and even protons the
building blocks of atoms will decay
most likely future is perhaps the most
dismal one where the universe becomes
cold and dark and empty as the universe
continues to expand and the galaxies
speed apart from each other space will
become empty and dead our own cluster of
galaxies will be moving away from us
faster than the speed of light and will
disappear from the night skies
eventually everything will just sort of
wind down them and that's the end of
things finally the universe will die and
all that will be left is a cold dark and
lifeless space
[Music]
you
I