over the past 50 years 3000 ships and a
hundred planes have gone missing in a
mysterious stretch of water in the
Atlantic Ocean one minute they are there
the next they've vanished they all have
one thing in common they all ventured
into the Bermuda Triangle
they are paradise destinations for
tourists the Sunshine Coast of Florida
and the Florida Keys the sun-baked
island of Puerto Rico and the Bahamas
and the beautiful coral seas of Bermuda
but the surrounding waters hold a
mystery that has been known by many
names
the devil's triangle the devil's seize
graveyard of the Atlantic but one name
given to these infamous waters strikes
fear into the hearts of those who
attempt to cross it
the Bermuda Triangle the Bermuda
Triangle lies off the eastern seaboard
of the United States bordered by the
Florida Keys Bermuda and Puerto Rico one
and a half million square miles of empty
ocean the Bermuda Triangle is a place
where people disappear mysteriously that
and it has no logical no conventional no
natural explanation but many scientists
believe there are logical explanations
extreme weather rare magnetic anomalies
affecting navigation and even gas
bubbles rising from the ocean floor it
is possible that bubbles from the ocean
floor can sink a ship and yet the
legends remain in places like Miami
where Navy aircraft disappeared on a
routine exercise that cost the lives of
27 men
how can you lose five aircraft and the
good questions the question is still
around today the Bahamas where one man
claims to have traveled through time we
experienced a spacetime warp of 100
miles in 30 minutes in Bermuda where
strange occurrences are said to affect
ships all my electronical instruments
went they went haywire and over the vast
Atlantic waters where pilots lose their
reason the plane was shuddering and the
instruments were gone and we didn't know
what the hell was going on
Miami the sunshine city
beautiful beaches a watersports paradise
it lies near the southeastern tip of the
Bermuda Triangle on the coast of Florida
Miami's beaches attract 11 million
visitors a year it's a departure point
for hundreds of cruise ships and flight
over the Bermuda Triangle half a century
ago another flight from here terrified
two young naval men
nineteen-year-old identical twins George
and David Rothschild were flying home
because of a sudden death in their
family reacted to the fact that we were
going to go to our father's funeral
the twins flew north from the Florida
Keys over the waters of the Bermuda
Triangle we've been flying for probably
20 or 30 minutes and all of a sudden the
pilot yelled out the instruments are
dead we have no more instruments and he
became very frantic with the instruments
malfunctioning the pilot had no idea
where he was or even how much gas
remained in the fuel tanks he said I'm
afraid we're going to run out of fuel
and he Howard to us please look out the
starboard window what can you see look
out the port window go back and forth
so in the meantime the plane was
shuttering and the instruments were gone
and we didn't know what the hell was
going on and he said can you see planes
can you see ships down there can you see
land anything please help us on this
the pilot became panic-stricken
the pilot said I'm too nervous I can't
fly so the copilot had to take over and
continue with the flight over water with
fuel running low the twins were also
getting desperate and we were looking
for some hope something to see but we
saw nothing all we saw was ocean we were
over the ocean finally after what seemed
like hours they spotted the coastline
when we finally got to Norfolk and they
landed then of course I was so happy I
kissed the ground that dirt that we were
on as a matter of fact Dave wouldn't fly
in a plane for over 20 years laughter
that that's really it
yeah the flight took place a decade
before the Bermuda Triangle earned its
infamous reputation we had no idea what
the brew muta triangle was or what the
effect of the bermuda triangle was and
later on we said that was it yeah we
were there in that one that's what
happened that's what affected our plane
unfortunately we survived it the pilot
of the rothschilds plane lost his nerve
because his instruments malfunctioned or
so he believed
but could the vast expanse of the
Bermuda Triangle have affected his mind
perhaps in his moment of madness he
believed the dials were broken because
they weren't telling him what his mind
was telling him
one man who knows how such confusion can
happen is flying instructor Robert grant
it's all part of the mind playing games
and you have to control it I've been
flying over water for several thousand
hours and when I get a long ways from
land the ears perk up you start hearing
sounds in the airplane that you haven't
heard since the last time you're over
open water grant is an expert on spatial
disorientation or vertigo the condition
where a pilot loses his sense of up and
down and left to right it starts to
panic
he flies over the Florida Keys the
southeastern tip of the Bermuda Triangle
here the afternoon heat haze can
disguise where the sea ends and the sky
begins we fly the airplane by outside
references in our main outside reference
that we fly by is the horizon we can
determine pitch up pitch down left and
right turn by looking out at the horizon
and without the horizon things become
very very difficult with the haze heavy
haze in the summer especially here we
can not differentiate between the sky
and the water there is no horizon and
that can lead to vertigo and the
confusion of vertigo can cause a pilot
to make completely irrational decisions
let's take for instance your airplane is
going in to say a right-hand turn your
mind is telling you that you are
actually going into a left-hand turn so
if you don't believe the instrument and
you believe your mind guess what happens
you turn more right and the more right
you turn the more vertigo sets in you
know spatial or disorientation is
another word that we use to describe
that and it's it's hard to explain
but let me tell you when it happens it's
a very scary thing and vertigo
unfortunately is kill people and if you
don't recover from what's happening and
believe your instruments and get the
plane straight and level you end up
crashing
and vertigo happens a lot more than we
care to admit miss basis
so could vertigo have been responsible
for the confusion of the rothschilds
pilot back in the 40s those those pilots
were aligned solely on a magnetic
compass and there was a certain amount
of guesswork involved and I certainly
take my hat off to those people that
flew back then because they had a lot of
guts to do what they did you get away
from land and you're strictly relying on
your compass for for Direction grant
believes the confusion that can be
develop islet over open water may
explain some of the bermuda triangle
disappearances well when you look at
history we've we've certainly lost ships
and we've lost airplanes in the area
called the Bermuda Triangle I call it
the den of inequity because you know
it's just so easy to to get lost out
there
an average of five planes still go
missing here every year but more than 50
years ago the Bermuda Triangle claimed
that many aircraft in just one day
Florida a magnet for Sun worshipers from
around the world but in 1945 the
beachgoers were military men and their
wives from Naval Air stations dotted
along the Florida coast
although the Second World War had ended
three months earlier
millions were still in the Armed Forces
memories of conflict were never far away
and the air was filled each day with TBM
Avenger bombers on training missions at
the Naval Air Station in Fort Lauderdale
rows of Avenger bombers stood ready but
one training mission was to lead to the
most perplexing Bermuda Triangle mystery
of all flight 19 the lost Patrol a
mystery studied for the past ten years
by author Gian quizar it was a to 10:00
p.m. in the afternoon December 5 1945
five Navy TBM Avenger bombers took off
from Naval Air Station Fort Lauderdale
for a routine training flight over the
Atlantic
the Avenger bomber was the Navy's
largest single engine plane and more
than able to handle the weather that day
of broken cloud and 12 miles visibility
as the five planes of flight 19 headed
out into the Bermuda Triangle 14 young
men were on board
Navy fliers like these pictured at the
base a few days earlier ironically the
flight was a routine lesson in advanced
navigation the route 316 nautical miles
took them east over hen and chickens
Shoals north over Bahamian islands and
westwards back to the base a course that
lay inside the Bermuda Triangle within
half an hour they reached their target
at Hanan chicken shoals and spent 20
minutes dropping practice bombs
but on the next leg of the exercise an
hour and a half into the mission the
leader flight lieutenant Charles Taylor
got into trouble he became completely
confused neither of his compasses were
working and he believed he was lost what
did you learn compass me
I don't know where we are
we must have come on that last turn what
does your compass rate I am lost at
present time I'm over small islands
believed to be the Florida Keys the
mission was familiar to naval
photographer John Evans I had made the
same flight that flight 19 made and
there was just nothing it was very
cinchy flight you go east mega one turn
then come back to the west how can you
get lost radio operators ashore could
hear the pilots but the lost pilots
could barely hear their base I'm sure
now that neither of my compasses are
working with the planes burning 70
gallons of gas an hour the radio
operators were helpless voyeurs to the
deadly drama unfolding in the skies
above the Bermuda Triangle my 270
degrees until we hit the beach run out
of gas
both planes play close formation when
one plane for up to 10 gallons of gas
both planes will land together we
ignored the landing site by 6:00 p.m.
with less than an hour's worth of fuel
remaining the radio messages became more
desperate
we may have to ditch we may have been
ditching any minute we may have to ditch
at four minutes past 7:00 a final faint
radio message was heard story Fox
sorry
it was the callsign of planes from the
Fort Lauderdale base then the radios
fell silent
with tanks drained of gas the five
Avenger bombers must have ditched in the
ocean
the Navy procedure was they one of the
planes got lost
everybody ditched the whole flight ditch
because it would be much easier to for
the search-and-rescue people to pick
these folks up the drills were constant
on saving your life after you ditched
you had flares you had my Mae West your
life jackets on despite worsening
weather conditions 242 planes searched
for days for the missing man
among the search team was Fort
Lauderdale naval pilot David White the
weather did get bad there was a front
that came through the wind changed but
for the first day we went out we
expected to see them floating out here
the TBM really was a good steady
airplane you could land them in the
water pull out the three-man life raft
and not even get your feet wet the
search covered more than a quarter of a
million square miles of ocean but found
nothing the flight never taught
anybody's knowledge made it back to land
no traces ever found in an intensive
search and that's basically the mystery
how can five aircraft disappear on a
very simple maneuver and there's simply
no trace ever found no way to really
understand what happened
so what could have happened to flight 19
many believe that with his compasses
mysteriously not working flight leader
Charles Taylor made a fatal and utterly
inexplicable error Taylor saw land below
him that he thought he recognized as
being in the Florida Keys an area he
knew well geez but almost certainly what
he saw was an island 200 miles away in
the Bahamas but even if Taylor did make
such an error of further flight 19
mystery remains
why would 13 other Airmen follow him
into thousands of square miles of empty
ocean he's the senior man you know he's
got thousands of hours in the air and
the students flop follow-the-leader
they that's their what they're taught to
do why one or two of them didn't defect
and say to hell with it rather be
court-martialed than to die
no one knows people say to me well what
if you'd been a student and and you knew
that he was wrong good question I
probably would have headed west and gone
back to Florida but the Bermuda Triangle
had not yet had its fill of tragedy that
day
a flying boat involved in the search
also vanished with 13 more men on board
an explosion was reported but no
wreckage was ever found
the first official inquiry into flight
19 s disappearance blamed lieutenant
Taylor the conclusion was that the
flight leader became so hopelessly
confused has to have suffered something
akin to a mental aberration a later
report cleared Taylor and concluded
cause unknown rumors circulated that
investigators had said it's as if
they've gone to Mars that's that's where
it all started and that's when the
people began to question how can you
lose five aircraft and it's good
questions the question that still is
around today blame it on aliens from out
of space or you can blame it on the
stupidity of the pilot well of course
I've heard the theories about they were
taking up the Mars but I can't see any
credibility to anything other than then
he got lost and they landed in the ocean
it should never have happened and that's
what gave rise to all these feeling
about the Bermuda Triangle or some alien
or some mist came in or whatever it was
more than half a century later
speculation continues every December 5th
at Fort Lauderdale they hold a memorial
service for the missing men but now
there are astonishing rumors that one
plane had successfully ditched and that
flight lieutenant Taylor could still be
alive I heard about two and a half years
ago that Taylor has survived
did they pay the Bohemians picked him up
and he was worried that he'd be blamed
for it but that would give credence to
the thought that why should I give I let
them know I'm still alive I might be
court-martialed and I think he would
have been
he finally married an island woman and I
it's an interesting serie and then every
time on the five December when they have
the memorial service I look around for
some guy about 78 79 80 and it's a
incredible thing to think about
it was the disappearance of flight 19
that first brought the Bermuda Triangle
to the public's attention but the
triangle was striking terror into the
hearts of men centuries earlier
new world explorers used to call this
the Isle of Devils because of the awful
screams and sounds that would emanate
from the island and especially at night
by the late 1950s the waters off the
Florida coast were infamous it was
rumored that those who ventured into the
triangle disappeared without trace
like the 14 young men of flight 19 the
area was first called the Bermuda
Triangle in 1955 since then many have
attempted to explain the mystery for
years one author has examined the facts
behind each missing ship and plane and
listed them all on his website he is
Gian quizar I first started merely to
document the Bermuda Triangle I was not
setting myself up to solve it or to
confirm any mystery I wanted to see if
it was still going on kazar discovered
that it is still going on
the question is why what is so sudden
that can cause a disappearance there
it's hard to say that's why there's the
great mystery of the triangle on average
60 ships and five planes go missing each
year in these mysterious waters it's a
mystery it's real-life mystery it's a
real-life detective story and you're
going to want to find the answer
Bermuda the island that gave its name to
the Bermuda Triangle
it's a beautiful but remote island 650
miles from the American mainland across
some of the world's most notorious
waters some of the greatest mysteries
have actually happened around Bermuda
some of the biggest vessels like Sylvia
loz 1976 was a five hundred ninety foot
vessel that apparently blew to pieces
after she signaled herself 140 miles
from Bermuda the cargo ship poet in 1980
after signaling north of Bermuda she
vanished
the weather was choppy but it was not
enough to cause a five hundred twenty
foot desolate sink without cause the
island is a sub tropical paradise
one-third the size of Washington DC
fringed with the purest pink coral sands
on earth
each year the 65,000 population swells
with half a million visitors
most of them Americans arriving by
cruise ship we just got married yeah
newly runs out on anyone I love it here
I love the beach the water is gorgeous
be they residents or visitor's they are
all greeted by one of the islands most
well-known fixtures Johnny Barnes
he's been here for decades and now he
has a statue in his honor the offshore
Bermuda reefs are home to a rich variety
of undersea life 600 species of fish
inhabit these waters it's a paradise for
scuba divers although with a few species
you don't want to meet unless they are
safely behind glass the bermuda aquarium
is one of the islands most popular
tourist attractions head of the aquarium
is native born Bermudian Jennifer Grey
Bermuda is the most beautiful place on
earth because we're an oceanic island
surrounded by pristine warm waters
there's not a lot of poverty there's not
a lot of crime
it's just a very exquisite island in
centuries past before the Bermuda
Triangle gained its notoriety
nobody wanted to land here it was a
fearful place prior to colonization in
the early 1600s new world explorers used
to call this the Isle of Devil's because
of the awful screams and sounds that
would emanate from the island and
especially at night and of course later
when they colonized the islands they
discovered that this noise was coming
from the endemic how very rare bird
that's known only to Bermuda and also
pigs that had come off of shipwrecks
not surprising then that young Islanders
are raised on legends of the Bermuda
Triangle I remember as a child myself
being absolutely in all of this this
somewhat scary Bermuda Triangle or hole
in space whatever it may be but of
course visitors are often hearing about
it for the first time and take it quite
seriously planes disappear and ships
disappear and you know all the stuff
that you hear on television through
movies but we're hoping that we're not
going to be one of those subjects we
don't want to disappear we want to enjoy
that rest of our lives well I've heard
that you know if you fly over the bureau
triangle or get anywhere close enough
for it yeah happen to disappear and no
one ever hears from you again the island
marks the northernmost point of the
Bermuda Triangle and here it is also at
its deepest we really are in very very
deep water and and it drops off around
us very steeply into nothing Bermuda is
a remote coral reef perched precariously
on top of a massive extinct volcano
surrounded by the vast Atlantic Ocean
more than a mile deep
one man who knows these waters well is
fisherman Sloane Wakefield and he has a
wary respect for the surrounding seas
the waters here you really have to know
them you don't want to be caught in an
area where there's reef and you're not
sure where you are because a boat
drawing any more than two feet of water
will run aground to describe it in a
nutshell it's treacherous Sloane and his
crewman Mark Moran catch wahoo and
mahi-mahi for local restaurants and
Marlin for sporting fun so what we do
when we're fishing is we run out to the
edge what we call the edge which would
be the side of the volcano and we troll
long anywhere from 4,000 feet of water
to 200 feet of water because that's how
sheer the drop-off is the fishermen
believe that some Bermuda Triangle
disappearances can be attributed to
natural causes like the weather because
we are a dot in the middle of the
Atlantic Ocean we get weather from
everywhere and it can change in a
heartbeat one minute we're looking at
good weather in the next minute you got
a low front coming through at one point
this year we saw probably fifteen maybe
twenty foot seas out there and you know
the boat meets like a feather on the
wind on those waves but in these waters
odd things can happen Wakefield has had
one experience he still can't explain
all my electronical instruments went
they went haywire
other
and once my instruments came back on
I was completely heading in the other
direction heading I was probably about
four miles past where I was supposed to
be
a lot of people were saying oh you your
instruments might have been shorting out
they've never shorted out before that
and they haven't shorted out since
that's the encounter that I personally
have had with what's called the Bermuda
Triangle
the waters known as the Bermuda Triangle
lie between the subtropical resorts of
Miami Bermuda and Puerto Rico thousands
of tourists are attracted here from all
over the world more than 800,000 crafts
are registered in Florida alone along
with countless other commercial vessels
and visiting cruise ships these waters
normally promise sunshine and calm seas
but sometimes there are hurricanes
Atlantic hurricanes are born off the
African coast feeding on energy and
moisture from the warm tropical waters
the tracks of these storms reveal how
over the past hundred years they head
for America and how often they veer off
towards the Bermuda Triangle
at the National Hurricane Center in
Miami the storms in the Bermuda Triangle
are studied by meteorologists such as
Jim Lu Xin
hurricanes are very frequent out in the
Bermuda Triangle area they're in fact
more hurricanes in a particular area
than any other in the Atlantic Basin and
a hurricane is a sailor's greatest fear
the Mariner may not know which way to
look
sometimes the weather may be coming from
one direction sometimes it may be coming
from the other direction in November
2001 the media besieged the Miami
weather center as hurricane Michelle
bore down on this corner of the triangle
regardless of where Michelle liked to go
as Michelle devastated the island of
Cuba residents were ordered to evacuate
the Florida Keys at the last moment
Michelle weakened a little and swerved
away into the Atlantic
the whole of Florida however was lashed
with rain
as night fell and the downpour reached
Miami tourists at South Beach celebrated
their narrow escape with a hurricane
party
but even events on a smaller scale than
hurricanes can be just as deadly
thunderstorms
thunderstorms are one plausible
explanation for some of the mysteries of
the Bermuda Triangle like the
disappearance of an historic ship in
1986 the Pride of Baltimore vanished
suddenly from radar screens 240 miles
north of Puerto Rico the disappearance
was a complete mystery then four days
and seven hours later eight survivors
were found they revealed that the ship
had been hit by a microburst hundred
mile an hour winds blasting from the
bottom of a freak thunderstorm there
were some very strong thunderstorms in
the area but what happened was a very
small scale microburst occurred right in
the vicinity of this tall ship which was
sunken in the downburst we think with
unfortunately a great loss of life and
that's that's what happens in these
downbursts and those are probably
responsible for some of the sinkings in
the ocean and in the Bermuda Triangle
but there are other even more
unpredictable dangers in the Bermuda
Triangle
waterspouts some water spouts are
tornadoes that move out to sea others
are formed when rotating columns of air
drop from thunder clouds to whip up a
vortex of spray the moisture condenses
forming a writhing column connecting the
sea to the clouds
could these elegant but dangerous
waterspouts account for some triangle
disappearances one man who might know
the answer is Jim Edd's a keen amateur
fishermen who chases and films water
spouts for fun
it's going to be coming across the frame
here really moving pretty good
quick quick run Oh beautiful I'm always
in search of that that the best
waterspout footage I can get get up
close on a boat filming from the air
perfect see the water coming up
you get a little smarter and you get a
little closer each summer monster
waterspout in open water water spouts
can be deadly particularly at night if
you're out there at night and a
waterspout develops it can flip your
vessel over and if it's a tornadic
waterspout the really big water spouts
the strong ones wants a high velocity
you may not see that
you may get stuck in it you may you may
hear it you may see you may feel the
water spray ring around you but there's
nothing you can do if you don't see it
certainly you can't rule out the
possibility of water spouts to explain
the disappearance of ships in the
Bermuda Triangle
as a fisherman Edd's knows of other
dangers within the Bermuda Triangle
when you're offshore in this area one of
the things you have to watch out for is
what we call rips those are areas
they're little Eddie's in the Gulf
Stream that the jack up the waves a lot
higher than what you're used to and
especially if the wind is blowing
against the current it can go from a two
to three foot surf maybe to a five to
six foot and when you get in there it's
just like a washing machine so you
really have to pay attention that you
don't slide down and nose down into a
wave
disappearances have been reported out
there for over 200 years before the
modern mystery of the triangle probably
the most famous is the USS Cyclops it
was a 1918 she carried wireless she had
309 US Navy crew aboard
she was a u.s. naval Collier and she
left
British Barbados enroute to Baltimore
and she never was seen again
it just went down as the greatest
mystery of the sea Woodrow Wilson the
president said only God in the sea knows
where the great ship has gone the
Bahamas a necklace of islands that lie
in the Atlantic Ocean a hundred miles
from the Florida coast here the weather
and the waters can be deceptively
beautiful what's interesting about the
disappearances in the Bahamas is that
the Bahama Bank is no more than 50 feet
shallow and yet no ship no aircraft has
been found on the bottom no trace has
ever been found of those that
disappeared the Bahamas attracts four
million visitors each year nearly half
the population work in the tourism
industry
boating is one of the most popular
attractions among the 700 islands only
23 of which are inhabited the main
danger around here is the Bahamas is a
very beautiful place and people often
get a false sense of security in terms
of the danger that they may face we have
cold fronts that sweep across from
Florida and in a matter of an hour can
change the weather from just the perfect
day to an absolute nightmare it often
means coastal boating can be quite
dangerous
vessel hailing Mayday this is Bahamas
air sea rescue now soar captain what is
the nature of distress in your location
over helping ships in distress in this
part of the triangle is the job of the
Bahamas air-sea rescue Association their
volunteer sailors see many baffling
cases but believe most are caused by
human error Bermuda Triangle level has
been fascinated with it people disappear
all the time it's easy to die out there
especially when there's no help my own
opinion is that although you don't know
exactly what happened in every case I
think almost every case is explainable
by human error I mean there are so many
ways to get yourself killed
on the sea to assume every time someone
is missing is due to a mysterious factor
I believe is stretching it but you never
know but perhaps there are forces other
than wind waves and weather affecting
the triangles waters
at the Bermuda underwater exploration
Institute are thousands of artifacts
raised from the ocean depths they come
from shipwrecks scattered around the
islands reefs but visitors also discover
that scientific theory has a part to
play in explaining the disappearances of
the Bermuda Triangle
the Institute's director is Ralph
Richardson there are some scientific
theories about the Bermuda Triangle one
includes the large pockets of gas which
because of seismic activity and so on
escape from the oceans bottom scientists
have discovered that huge bubbles of
methane gas can violently erupt without
warning from the ocean floor you can
imagine a ship sailing through sailing
on the ocean and a large pocket of gas
that just surrounds it the ship then
loses its buoyancy and disappears from
sight without warning that is one of the
theories of the Bermuda Triangle at
least one oil rig is thought to have
been sunk by a methane gas eruption but
nobody knew whether the bubbles could
actually sink a ship at sea
Bruce DiNardo an expert in fluid
dynamics at the Naval Postgraduate
School in Monterey California is now
researching just how dangerous those
bubbles can be let's imagine the body
that's floating in water
the reason it's floating a body that's
heavier than air is that the greater you
depth you are the greater the pressure
so a body along its bottom is going to
feel this greater pressure and the
pressure will keep it floating if you
add bubbles you lower the density of the
water the bubbles take up space the
volume of the water will expand but the
mass of the water stays the same so the
buoyant force will decrease as I
increase the amount of bubbles the ball
will sit deeper in the fluid and
eventually we get to a critical point
where the ball sinks
now what might happen in the ocean is
that there is a burst of bubbles we can
show that here I just turn on and turn
off the air
you can see that the ball sinks if this
were a ship and it took on enough water
it would sink to the bottom and stay
there in the ocean there is something
like a methane eruption the source of
bubbles will be localized they will rise
but there'll be water outside where
there are no bubbles but the fact that
we can it can sink there is from to me
that's proof that have ship can sink in
the ocean I don't need to say I wouldn't
even say theoretically I mean it is
possible that bubbles from the ocean
floor can sink a ship methane gas
eruptions may account for some missing
ships but they can never answer all the
questions I believe we will solve it
eventually so long as we don't deny that
it does go on but there is one story of
the Bermuda Triangle that seems to defy
every rational explanation a tale that
if true would bend the very laws of
nature
the waters of the Bermuda Triangle
infamous and mysterious but do more
ships and planes vanish here than
anywhere else on earth what sets the
triangle apart from other oceans is that
there is a higher number of
disappearances of both ships and
aircraft in the area there are other
sections of ocean where there is
comparable traffic where there where the
coastguard answers an equal number of
May days but in the Triangle there is a
greater proportion of disappearances
where nothing is found there is no SOS
usually there's no electronic Maydays
issued there's no trace found in most
instances and those disappearances has
spawned some fantastic theories there
are those who believe that UFOs from
outer or inner space are kidnapping
people there are those who believe that
the electromagnetic phenomena are
capable of causing dimensional
transmutations and time warps time
tunnels they're all reported out there
one of those time discrepancies is said
to have happened here in the Bahamas
property developer Bruce Gernon has been
flying to and from here for more than 30
years but no flight was his strange as
the one he made with his father on the
4th of December 1970 father and son
planned to fly from Andrews Town Airport
in the Bahamas heading more than a
hundred miles across the sea to Palm
Beach the weather was fine as they took
off just after 3 p.m. the first unusual
thing that I saw that day was a
lenticular cloud that was hovering over
the Great Bahama Bank at least 60,000
feet high and my airplane wasn't capable
of flying over it it was very intense
with huge flashes going on rapidly at a
random pace I noticed an opening in the
clouds like a huge huge a Pope Ihnen
but as I approached it the top of the
opening closed and it became a
horizontal tunnel it appeared to be
between 10 and 15 miles long and when
the aircraft entered the tunnel these
lines appeared and they were rotating
counterclockwise it was difficult to
keep it level and concentrate on the
other end of the tunnel which was aiming
directly for Miami Gernon says he
emerged from the tunnel to find it
closing behind him his airplane soon
became engulfed in a peculiar mist I
checked my instruments and they didn't
appear to be working well he claims that
once inside this mist the airplane
disappeared air traffic control he says
could no longer see him on their radar
screens we were caught inside this
strange fog with the instruments
malfunctioning and air-traffic control
are unable to help us and then the air
traffic controller came back on the
radio screaming that he had an airplane
directly over Miami Beach
I looked at my watch and we had only
been flying just over 30 minutes so we
should still be at least 80 or 90 miles
away from Miami Gernon landed at 3:48
p.m. landed in Palm Beach and the
flighted took only 45 minutes and I made
that flight dozens of times before and
it always took about an hour and 20
minutes sometimes it an hour-and-a-half
Gernon has never been able to come up
with a rational explanation for how he
made the flight so quickly but despite
the skepticism of others he has never
stopped searching for an answer
well after researching it for many years
I have come to the conclusion that we
experienced a space-time warp of 100
miles in 30 minutes just didn't make
sense until I started researching a time
and what it can do and forget a triangle
the flight changed garnon's life he is
now writing a book about the experience
Miami Bermuda Puerto Rico and the
Bahamas are all popular tourist
destinations attracting travelers from
around the globe
most enter and leave the Bermuda
Triangle in safety but still the mystery
remains pilot error water spouts
hurricanes rip tides thunderstorms time
warps and disorientation all possible
explanations for this seemingly
inexplicable mystery the mystery of the
Bermuda Triangle
you